
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <channel>
   <title>BlitzLiving</title>
   <link>./</link>
   <description>Recent content on BlitzLiving</description>
   <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
   <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2019 - Author Name</copyright>
   <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
   
       <atom:link href="./index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
   
     <item>
       <title>From A Hackerfarm To YCombinator</title>
       <link>./posts/hackerfarm-to-ycombinator/</link>
       <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>./posts/hackerfarm-to-ycombinator/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine a farmhouse, with cattles, hen, ducks, and trees, lots and lots of trees, from mangoes and jackfruits to wild bushes, alongside huts made of tree trunks and coconut leaves…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now put some high-speed 4G routers, a couple of solar panels, electric unicycles and then top it off with a bunch of hackers living there. How does it look like in your mind?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unimaginable, a place so removed from the cusp of modernity yet at the very edge of an internet revolution, with people working on Ethereum (&lt;a href=&#34;https://ezether.com/),&#34;&gt;https://ezether.com/),&lt;/a&gt; machine learning and electric mobility. And then add oodles of yoga&amp;amp;meditation and there you have it, the ultimate place to live and work on mindblowing stuff. That&amp;rsquo;s the hackerfarm run Jaaga situated just 20kms on the outskirts of the Silicon Valley of India in Kodathi, Bengaluru.The place started by Freeman Murray, an early SWE at Sun Microsystems and co-founder of Kendara.com (acq.) turned social entrepreneur who advised and started several accelerator and incubators in India. He started this novel space in 2010 with to impart programming skills to kids from under-represented places in India. Beginning with a cohort of 10 students, mostly high school and college dropouts, the hackerfarm has come a long way with more than 300 people who have visited or studied here, also, becoming a popular hub with Digital Nomads as well. In Jan 2017, my eighth semester of college, I applied to become a resident and work on some side projects in a place where I can work and collaborate with likeminded people and Jaaga seemed like the perfect place for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;Hackers hacking away on a typical evening!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;Jazzing up the camp with neon lights during party nights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But, what I didn&amp;rsquo;t have in mind was how invigorating the hacker farm experience would turn out to be and how the farm would shape my destiny over the next few years - more on that towards the end!Freeman&amp;rsquo;s no.1 rule for staying in the hacker farm is waking up before 8am everyday and a mandatory hour of Yoga under the tree in the Ashram. Having no experience of  Yoga before, the one-hour session was initially difficult but watching Freeman changing postures so gracefully inspired me to practice hard to imitate his style. Gradually I started sitting there longer doing meditation even after the compulsory one-hour session was over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The kitchen was run by all of us on a rotational basis with a team of 4, taking care of cooking and cleaning. After the 9 am breakfast, everybody can be seen working in the study area, ready to build and break stuffs.The farm was a communal experience in its entirety.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;The workspace!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were people from all stages of their career, from college dropouts, digital nomads, freelancers, top-tier executives like Akash  who quit his job to learn to code to people running six-figure businesses. There are no rigid rules to what you work on but if you do decide to follow a curriculum, Rajanshu (Sunny) Ujjwal runs the boot camp for Javascript mentoring beginners on the MERN track. At the end of every quarter is a demo-day, where everyone demos the things they have been working on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;tech-enabled-learning-for-allages&#34;&gt;Tech-enabled Learning for all ages&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freeman, being an open-source enthusiast, urges everyone to contribute to open source and push everything they work on during the quarter to the Github. Some of the projects worked on by various residents of Jaaga &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Jaaga&#34;&gt;https://github.com/Jaaga&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker5.jpg#float-left&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freeman, is pretty passionate about enabling learning through technology. He started a program called CyberScouts, where he urged volunteers to teach kids from rural schools. We formed teams and adopted a school to teach kids for 4 hours every week. In rural India, most students lack basic arithmetic and language skills, we met kids who were in Grade 3 but didn&amp;rsquo;t know arithmetic or English alphabets. In some schools in far off villages, students from Grade 1–5 were packed in a single room and taught by a single teacher. It was really disappointing to see the state of affairs. Freeman had over 100+ Android tablets installed with various learning games, puzzles and a math learning app developed by ex-Jaaga residents. We went to the schools twice a week and spent hours teaching the English alphabet, basic arithmetic and logical thinking through games like Lightbot and Cut the Rope&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker6.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker7.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;Kids competing with each other to solve arithmetic problems in a dual-fight mode!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These three kids all from Grade 2, I personally took it as a challenge to have them recite all the alphabets in the English language.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker9.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within 2 weeks, all three of them could recite the alphabets and therefore this celebratory moment :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-unicycleclub&#34;&gt;The Unicycle Club&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just when you thought, things couldn&amp;rsquo;t get any more interesting, you would see residents of Jaaga riding through the village roads on electric unicycles. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XyuU7fP1KvU&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XyuU7fP1KvU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freeman got them imported from China and wanted people to start adopting them throughout Bangalore as an environment-friendly means of transportation. Faster than bicylces, more portable than Segaway long before bicyle-sharing and escooters became a thing in India. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker10.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A workshop on assembling Unicycles&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-jaaga&#34;&gt;After Jaaga&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;starting-icohunt-withsaurav&#34;&gt;Starting ICOHunt with Saurav&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Soon after Jaaga, Saurav and me started ICOHunt, a side project that Saurav and me were using to track our investments in different ICOs. Back during the ICO boom, many friends started asking us for advice and we thought we could create a marketplace for tokens and the idea was to make it a one-stop place to invest and track your tokens. We almost made it to an accelerator in Netherlands but we decided to play safe as we knew sooner or later regulators especially SEC would be on our ass. The project still lives and run by bots!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;evangelizing-decentralization-indelhi&#34;&gt;Evangelizing Decentralization in Delhi&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Courtesy of our friends at TLabs and HelloMeets, we started advocating for cryptocurrencies, especially programming on top of decentralization protocol in Delhi. In a matter of weeks, we had 256 developers on Whatsapp sharing knowledge and organizing meetups for cryptocurrency projects. Check out one of our FB Live session.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker12.jpeg#mid&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at BlockHack, Pankaj Jain moderating the event.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker11.jpeg#mid&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saurav and Me at fullhouse event at InvestoPad&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker13.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a hackathon sponsored by Facebook in Hyderabad in Aug 2017 which was won by Saurav and me, Harshit (ex-Jaaga) was in a team with Rachit (a classmate of mine from high school). Within the next few months, Rachit, Saurav and me became super close because of our shared love for discussing philosophy :P and cryptonetworks. We introduced Rachit to the ethos of decentralization and he ended up spending  hours with us discussing about the UX of dApps because of his background as a user experience designer at Samsung/IIT Guwahati. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;launching-dexstack&#34;&gt;Launching DexStack&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker15.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2018, me and Aviraj Khare started hacking together a decentralized exchange on top 0x. But, again due to regulatory issues, we took it down but some folks from the crypto community started reaching out to us to ask if we could help them build an exchange. We already had everything, the smart contracts, the front-end, the backend systems. So we launched it as a servic and it helped us sail through the Crypto winter!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;seeding-authlayer&#34;&gt;Seeding AuthLayer&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fast forward Nov 2018, I switched to an iPhone and lost the features provided by a money-management app called MoneyView in India. Even though Mint was launched in 2007 in the US. There wasn&amp;rsquo;t a single app for consumers to track their finances in India. I started looking for ways to solve the problems of fetching transactions and came across the Open Banking PSD/2 regulation in the US. My first thought was, how cool would it be if I could just &amp;ldquo;Sign-in with HDFC Bank&amp;rdquo; on to an app! Thankfully, HDFC Bank had an Open Banking portal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker16.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I reached out to Rachit and fortunately, he had recently quit his job and he was equally excited about the idea of creating a single interoperable ecosystem between banks and fintechs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After two months of talking to other fin-tech startups and getting them on-board for the goal of using Transaction APIs directly from banks, we set up meetings with the Chief Digital Officers of all the major banks in India and spent the first half of March negotiating with them. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./hacker17.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AuthLayer at Fintegrate 2019&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We got our first 3 enterprise pilot customers at Fintegrate 2019 and got our first acqhuire-offer!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the very last day, we applied to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ycombinator.com&#34;&gt;YCombinator&lt;/a&gt; and after 2 rounds of interviews, we were selected for their S19 batch! &lt;img src=&#34;./hacker18.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s Saurav and me at the hackerfarm in 2017!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Deciding What To Build NEXT?</title>
       <link>./posts/on-building-a-new-product/</link>
       <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>./posts/on-building-a-new-product/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/hello-meets/deciding-what-to-build-next-ac15afd1bcdd&#34; title=&#34;Permalink to Deciding What To Build NEXT? – HelloMeets – Medium&#34;&gt;Reposted from my original post Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;deciding-what-to-build-next--hellomeets--medium&#34;&gt;Deciding What To Build NEXT? – HelloMeets – Medium&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Product Managers are an interesting lot. Talk to any PM about their product and they would have a hundreds of different ideas about features they want to add to their product.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With hundreds of ideas and feature requests from users inundating a PM’s ideabook, &lt;strong&gt;the question that often bothers a PM is deciding what to build next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add to it the fact that over-complicating and adding too many features to the app not only adds to the complexity of the app but also impacts the User Experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most essential rule for Product Management is to let the user find what he is looking for in the shortest amount of time. Any obstacle in the process only leads to dropoffs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;We talked to some of the seasoned Product Managers from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hellomeets.com&#34;&gt;HelloMeets&lt;/a&gt; Community and this is the number one rule they live by — ”Build to solve the pain points of your users”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We asked them, how they found the pain points of their users.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;user-interviews&#34;&gt;User Interviews&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/0*VBthbPL1ydb0e1sw.&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feedback from your users is the best way to identify the pain points in your app.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gagan Mahajan, PM at Sheroes says he lives by user interviews. He calls his new users within a week of their registration and asks them if they found what they were looking for! We think, that’s a pretty effective way to solicit feedback. But, most often, there will be many people who sign up for your services and apps passively without any ideas of what they are looking for. So, in order to get the most valuable feedback from your users, your User Interviews should be structured.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sahil Pruthi, Product Manager at Traveltriangle who has brought massive growth in the android &amp;amp; iOS apps in the last 2 years has the following advice:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1. **Fixed group discussions: &lt;strong&gt;He&lt;/strong&gt; **brings 4–5 of his past travellers together and gets them to talk. Through this he gets amazing insights on the various problems a user faces, and the priority because he see people relating to each others problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2. &lt;strong&gt;Face to Face interview:&lt;/strong&gt; Typically 45 min — 1 hour interview with the user to understand the pain points. Build an empathy map and buyer persona.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some good sources to know more about this are :&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uxpin.com/studio/blog/the-practical-guide-to-empathy-maps-creating-a-10-minute-persona/&#34;&gt;The Practical Guide to Empathy Maps Creating a 10 Minute User Persona&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@harrybr/how-to-run-an-empathy-user-journey-mapping-workshop-813f3737067&#34;&gt;How to run an empathy User Journey Mapping workshop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;3.** Be a User Yourself:** Eat your own dog food. In his case, he booked a trip and kept taking note of the problems he faced.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;4. &lt;strong&gt;If you’re a tech company selling some product, make it a practice to stay with folks that sell the product.&lt;/strong&gt; This way you’ll be better able to understand a lot of problems that a consumer faces. He says, In my case, I make it a regular practice to spend time with the operations people/travel agents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;focus-on-the-outcomes-not-the-industry&#34;&gt;Focus on the outcomes, not the industry&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This point is oft-repeated in the industry but gets quite lost during the product development. Product Managers mostly look at the products of their competitors or the industry as a whole. Thus, their product roadmap gets filled with features some of which are not even relevant to the users.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The most important thing you have to remember as a Product Manager is that you create solutions to the problems faced by your users.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you’re building or managing a new product, you have to believe you can create a better solution that people will want to use because it delivers a better outcome for them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;A strong understanding of the outcome customers want, and how they currently get it, is essential for you to succeed in product management.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focusing on outcome, rather than category, industry, or product type, lets you understand your real competitors. The second a company focuses on “the industry it’s in” rather than the “outcome it delivers”, it loses touch, and shortly after, loses customers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Think of the outcomes that your app is trying to achieve and find how those outcomes are currently being met by your users.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Research what solutions they’re using, and breakdown the steps required to achieve those same outcomes by using your app.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example: Some people want to stay informed about latest news without actually reading the whole 500 word article. Now they have &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@inshorts_in&#34;&gt;inshorts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arranging a taxi in a city used to involve calling many numbers until you found a company with availability, followed by a lengthy dialogue about your location, destination and required arrival time. Now, you can call a cab with the press of a button via &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@Uber&#34;&gt;Uber&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@Olacabs&#34;&gt;Olacabs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t have to be as revolutionary as the ones mentioned, but there are hundreds of different things that your users are currently doing in their day-to-day life. &lt;strong&gt;Your job as a Product Manager is to figure out how you can help your customers get the same outcome or albeit a better one in the shortest amount of time possible.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jeff Bezos is famous for saying “focus on the things that don’t change”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The problems that people and businesses encounter don’t change often. The ways they can be solved changes almost yearly.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So it stands to reason that making things people want should start with the “what people want” bit, and not the more tempting “things we can make”.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;prioritization&#34;&gt;Prioritization&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/0*Ou_9A1bq_hIRJMeF.&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prioritization of the features is extremely important.&lt;/strong&gt; You have to build products based on how impactful the feature will be on a customer’s life. The second axis is based on a customer’s expectations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you build features that are expected from your app, it can fall in 2 categories:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Must-Have: These are features that are essential for your app and they have the most impact in the user’s life.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who-Cares: These are features that are nice to have but doesn’t really create significant impact.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;And, if you decide to go above and beyond and decide to build something extraordinary, it can either delight your users so much that they react with “WOW!” or doesn’t create significant impact but they still love it and call it a “Neat” move.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For example, when Whatsapp launched “Stories” in their app, it didn’t really create any significant impact in their user’s life, instead it backfired though some users still called it a neat move.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As startups, it is important for you to always aim for the “WOW” reaction from your users. But this should not be at the cost of “Must-Have” features.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.productplan.com/strategies-prioritize-product-features/&#34;&gt;For a more in depth explanation of various techniques for prioritization, take a look here.&lt;/a&gt; via &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@productplan&#34;&gt;ProductPlan&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@jimsemick&#34;&gt;Jim Semick&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;deriving-meaning-from-metrics&#34;&gt;Deriving meaning from Metrics&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/0*nLYhTJ2rlEkDHkCP.&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;**Product Managers live by Metrics and KPIs (Key Performance Indicators). **But, with multiple metrics and analytics to look at, it becomes important to prioritize what metrics are important for you and your company. A business in general can has any of the following goals:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Increase the DAU&lt;br&gt;Daily Active Users, as the name suggests gives you an estimate of the no. of users who are using your app everyday. Of all the different metrics, DAU is one of the most important factor for the success of your app. Some app developers can get a huge boost in the number of downloads of their app pretty quickly by having a large marketing budget and spending money on incentivized app downloads. But, it is commonly known, across all industries, &lt;strong&gt;80%&lt;/strong&gt; of all app users churn within 90 days.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://info.localytics.com/blog/mobile-apps-whats-a-good-retention-rate&#34;&gt;To know more about what’s a Good Retention Rate, look here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2. Increase the time spent by the user in the app&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;3. Increasing Retention&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The graph below showcases the average retention rate by industry after 30, 60, and 90 days respectively. As you can see, the average retention rate varies by industry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Currently, Media &amp;amp; Entertainment apps retain the most users on average, with a 24% retention rate post 90 days.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/0*DSxfhdb3FQ6XrUjm.&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Source: Localytics&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So the question becomes, how do we improve the retention?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;With the advent of various in-app engagement solutions, real-time push notifications and improvement in the location-based marketing capabilities, there are myriad of ways you can take advantage of them to improve user engagement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;4. Increase Conversion in case of m-commerce app&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once again Gagan and Sahil agree that you should be clear about what you want the user to accomplish in your platform. Break it down into multiple steps, track how many users are reaching each step and see where they are dropping off more than usual.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example: Check where you have the most no. of drop-offs in your sales funnel i.e from the time your user conducts a search to the point where your user completes the payment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;High number of searches, low number of product view means that you need to work on search results relevance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is important to break the user into product funnels → a visitor to lead to activated to conversion.&lt;/strong&gt; There are various tools to understand and leverage these analytics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use Heatmaps / Live user action videos, funnel analytics to understand the drop offs in the various stages of the funnel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But, it’s very easy to get lost in optimizing your site or app by picking up the wrong metrics. Therefore Sahil points out that it is very important for you to have a structure in mind of the various stages the user is in. And then bucket the problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;complexity-cost-of-your-features&#34;&gt;Complexity Cost Of Your Features&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://firstround.com/review/The-one-cost-engineers-and-product-managers-dont-consider/&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@firstround&#34;&gt;First Round&lt;/a&gt;, Kris Gale, VP Engineering at Yammer talks about out how features can create complexity cost in an engineering organization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Complexity cost is the debt you accrue by complicating features or technology in order to solve problems. An application that does twenty things is more difficult to refactor than an application that does one thing, so changes to its code will take longer. Sometimes complexity is a necessary cost, but only organizations that fully internalize the concept can hope to prevent runaway spending in this area.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;He goes further and talks about how often Product Managers use the phrases, “how hard would it be…” and “can’t you just…” during their conversation with engineers. These phrases reflect very poorly on the product managers. What might take two weeks right now adds a marginal cost to every engineering project we’ll take on in this product in the future. In fact, I’d argue that the initial time spent implementing a feature is one of the least interesting data points to consider when weighing the cost and benefit of a feature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Therefore, as a Product Manager, you should also carefully discuss the engineering complexity of the feature and the codebase that needs to be changed in order to support the feature. And of course, don’t forget to do a cost benefit analysis of the time your developers would need to spend developing the feature with the time they could have spent working on some other low hanging fruits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some of our upcoming meetups:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/leWujG%27&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measuring Design Success — 20th May — Bengaluru&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/zH3OAy&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Startup Hiring Event — 28th May- Delhi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@sahilpruthi&#34;&gt;Sahil Pruthi&lt;/a&gt; and Gagan Mahajan for sharing their insights with &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@hellomeets&#34;&gt;HelloMeets&lt;/a&gt; Community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Why Startup?</title>
       <link>./posts/why-startup/</link>
       <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>./posts/why-startup/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;When do you decide to do startup? Is starting up intentional or is it a result of doing things that you like out of natural curiosity and unintentionally stumbling upon an opportunity that you decide to capitalize on hoping a home run :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s the question that have bugged me for quite a long time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The common answer seems to be that you create products to solve a pain problem that you have faced or a pain problem that you have discovered others have.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;there-could-be-multiple-reasons-to-startup&#34;&gt;There could be multiple reasons to startup:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Solve a pain point for yourself that you discovered on your own either through experimenting with a lot of stuff or because of talking to people in your network. Eg. Slack&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Be naturally curious about something and dig deeper, peeling layers after layer until you invent a novel/breakthrough idea that didn’t exist before and then productize it and launch. Eg. The Page Rank algorithm developed by Sergey and Larry that gave birth to Google.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keep building cool things out of your own need to create and launch it in the wild. If it takes off, you raise money and blitzscale or you you bootstrap if people starts paying you. Eg. SnapChat, Whatsapp and Facebook&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You are a visionary/missionary and you have a vision for the world and therefore you go all out in turning your vision into reality. Either this vision is of a technology that you want to bring to life or a mission to radically change the way society works. Eg. SpaceX, Bitcoin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is another approach, a recent phenomenon - “The Maker movement” popularized by &lt;a href=&#34;https://indiehacker.com&#34;&gt;IndieHackers&lt;/a&gt; and the remote-work community, where you create a sustainable business that makes you enough profits to quit your job and work full-time on your product. Eg. All the products on Indie Hackers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cost of starting a software company has radically gone down in the last few years and there are examples of bootstrapped-one-person software companies making &amp;gt;$1mn in ARR. Just goto Indie Hackers and read through the interviews with over hundreds of makers bootstrapping their software companies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But even though the cost of starting up has decreased, the cost of distribution has increased manifold. You can’t just create a shabby looking product and hope people will start using it. The whole lean products movement seems nice but in order to really make something useful, you need to spend a considerable amount of time in making your product fast and beautiful if you are building anything for mass consumer space. With all the fancy new apps with beautiful user interfaces that most internet users are used to, it’s hard to hold their attention unless your product is delightful to use. Ofcourse, it depends a lot on the alternatives that exist and &lt;strong&gt;“How”&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;“What”&lt;/strong&gt; pain points is your product solving for your target users.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may or may not need money to start a company and you should definitely not let money stop you from really making the things you want. There is a lot I could say about this whole dilemma of to raise or to not raise, but that’s a topic for another day!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>The Product Manager Workflow</title>
       <link>./posts/pm-workflow/</link>
       <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>./posts/pm-workflow/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./workflow.png&#34; alt=&#34;PM Workflow&#34;&gt;Having a shared understanding of the Product Development process at any startup is arguably one of the most important thing at a startup. At a very early stage when there are just 4 founders, hacking together a product, having a streamlined process of planning, roadmapping and QA might not be hugely important. In fact, putting up a process could actually hinder product development as features may get stuck at the planning phase and there would always be something more to work on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But as a team grows in size and you have more than 2 PMs in the team and a shared engineering team, having a streamlined PM workflow is a no-brainer. At my last workplace, after six months, the Senior PM and the engineering team quickly became overwhelmed at the rate of new feature requests coming up from the management and other teams. Our workflow before I put the following in process was docs on Dropbox Paper, where the whole team ideated and hammered the specification and then our designer would come in and work with Product to flesh out designs that would then be uploaded to Zeplin and attached to a ticket on Jira.#Ideas can come from anywhere&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ideas are really important in an early stage startup and therefore, as a PM you should be open-minded about incoporating ideas from the whole team but prioritizing is what your job should be. In order for the whole team to have a shared mission and feel inclusive, I created a board on Trello, “Product Pipeline”. I divided the board into columns depending on the product area that feature/idea would fall under.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At Ceekr, being a social platform, we had a lot of areas - User Engagement &amp;amp; Growth - Partners (for our partners) - Backend Optimization - Monetization - Mobile&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-product-pipeline&#34;&gt;1. Product Pipeline&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is where the whole team comes together to post their ideas. Pipeline The board is organized into multiple lists to make it easier for the product team to categorize all the ideas that are added to the Board. Most people can add their suggestions to a generic list called Inbox, from where the Product team can pick up the cards, sort them or move them to the next board which is Roadmap for further discussions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-product-roadmap&#34;&gt;2. Product Roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./trello1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Trello&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Board is a high level overview of the features for the PRODUCT over the next 6 months.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Next Up list is where the ideas or features to be implemented are added from the Pipeline or prioritised needs from Important Stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Cards from the next-up list is shifted to the Ideation list once brainstorming or discussions begin on their specific goals and results. Once the features are ideated upon, their Specs and the efforts required are attached to the cards and then based on the Efforts Estimated and our timeline, it is further classified into the following lists:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Approved for Development pipeline for this Quarter&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Added to the backlog for This Quarter&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Or if the estimated effort is too high and the impact factor is low, it’s added to either Next&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Quarter or Future.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-product-planning&#34;&gt;3. Product Planning&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This board is where the items from Roadmap are brought in for detailed specification and design.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The specification document is fully optimized and added to Confluence and the Designs are discussed, reviewed and the Zeplin links are attached to the cards and then it is sent for development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-development-progress&#34;&gt;4. Development Progress&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Board loosely mirrors the Development of Features or Epics/Stories from Jira.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The feature requests from the Planning board are added to the Backlogs, and from Backlogs, I would create a detailed specifications doc on Confluence and attach the relevant, Epics or Stories in Jira.After that our Engineering Manager would divide the Epics/Stories into appropriate Task/Sub-tasks and the Issue No. is attached with the appropriate card.Thereafter its a matter of moving the Cards into the appropriate progress list mirroring the lifecycle of that Card with respect to Jira.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-bugs&#34;&gt;5. Bugs&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;And for all the bugs that people catch, we put it on this board and from there we would collaborate with the Engineering to create relevant tickets on Jira.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>BlockGiving - A decentralized giving network</title>
       <link>./posts/blockgiving/</link>
       <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>./posts/blockgiving/</guid>
       <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;colony-hackathon-submission&#34;&gt;Colony Hackathon Submission&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A decentalized, self-perpuating, cross-border giving network on top of COLONY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;goal&#34;&gt;Goal:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;To create a self-perpetuating, decentralized, cross-borders, Giving Platform.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We aim to create a platform where users can create projects, work on projects and fund projects to help people around the globe.By the nature of design of the platform, there is a complete transparency in the way the funding works and the way funds are disbursed.People in the grassroots can directly take up tasks and get funded instantly for the service provided.The community as a whole evaluates the task completion submissions and approves or disapproves it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/blockgiving/blockGiving/master/colony/assets/flow.png&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;problems-with-large-ngos&#34;&gt;Problems with Large NGOs&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Donors don’t see the real impact of how their funds are getting used immediately.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Some donors might be more passionate about certain cause and he/she might not be willing to donate to a large NGO because he might feel his contributions are insignificant. But, by using our platform he/she can fund small Actions of Goodness and see the impact in a short time.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;There is no transparency on how the funds are being disbursed&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-solution&#34;&gt;The Solution&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Allow anyone to Create Projects concerning a particular social issue(&lt;em&gt;Domains in Colony&lt;/em&gt;) by staking ETH.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Allow anyone to Create Actionable Tasks related to a particular project by staking ETH.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Allow anyone to Take up tasks, submit proof of work in the form of images and videos&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Allows the Creators of the Tasks/Evaluators to validate tasks&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do-ers claim funds after task validation and gets ETH directly into their wallet.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;you-can-access-it-live-at-httplocalhost8080&#34;&gt;You can access it live at http://localhost:8080/&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;You should have MetaMask installed and connected to Rinkeby Test Network to view Project Funds and Create New Project.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;While funding New Project, Enter Atleast 0.1 ETH to Create a New Project.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-hackathon-results&#34;&gt;Our Hackathon Results&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/blockgiving/blockGiving/master/colony/assets/rank.png&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;./colony_judges_comments.md&#34;&gt;Comments from Judges &lt;/a&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;We ended up 4th with a prize of $1000, we just put in 10 hours of work into this project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lessons learned: Don&amp;rsquo;t start too late!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;walkthrough&#34;&gt;Walkthrough&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;./BlockGivingDeck.pdf&#34;&gt;Take a look at the whole deck and the walkthrough&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;setup&#34;&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;clone the repo&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;install python, pip and virtualenv&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;pip install django&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;cd colony&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;python manage.py makemigrations&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;python manage.py migrate&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;python runserver 0.0.0.0:8080&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;things-to-do&#34;&gt;Things to do&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Auto assign task to anyone through permissioned smart contract (similar to how Create Project smart contract)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Task Validation/Submission front-end views left to be implemented due to deadline.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Notes from Learning How to Learn</title>
       <link>./posts/notes-learning-how-to-learn/</link>
       <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>./posts/notes-learning-how-to-learn/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;Notes from the fantastic course on&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&#34; alt=&#34;Learning How To Learn&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;INTRO/FOCUSED VS. DIFFUSED THINKING&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Can only be in one or the other&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Diffused&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;when writing, write in diffuse mode, edit in focused mode&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;to engage diffuse brain - before writing, mind-mapping/clustering - take a paper, hold landscape&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;when you write, you want to create new things, think of new relationships.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;DON&amp;rsquo;T EDIT WHILE YOU WRITE&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;writeordie.com - good to break the habit of editing while writing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Dali + Edison - diffuse mode to think about ideas, fall asleep, wake up and go into focused mode&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;when you&amp;rsquo;re learning something difficult, your mind needs to go back and forth between the two different learning modes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;need to do a little work every day, gradually growing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Procrastination &amp;amp; Sleep&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Pomodoro technique - set timer for 25 minutes, turn off all interruptions, and then focus. Then 5 minutes reward. Then start again.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Learn something right before you sleep. You might dream about it, which will enhance learning&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Abstract&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Build and strengthen abstract ideas through practice&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Practice makes permanent&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;When you first learn something like how to solve a problem, the connection is weak. But if you practice, you begin deepening that pattern. When you have a problelm down cold, the pattern is like a dark firm pattern between neurons&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;When learning:&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;study hard by learning intently&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;then relax&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Memory&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;2 major systems: Long term memory vs. working memory&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Working memory - what you&amp;rsquo;re immediately and consciously processing in your mind (through prefontal cortex) - mind can hold around 4 chunks&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Long term memory - like a storage warehouse, stored around large parts of the brain. Immense, can hold billions of items. Where you store fundamental concepts and techniques.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;when you learn something new, use working memory. then practice. will then be stored into long term memory&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Spaced repetition - learn/repeat learning over several days&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Learning&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Learn more by active engagement than passive listening&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use exercise to get into diffuse mode&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Even in adulthood, new neurons are being formed in your hippocampus&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;connections between neurons can be strengthened by being in an active, social environment. alternatively, exercise will do this!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Being in a creative environment helps! Talk to people, explain ideas, can boost the creative process&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Creativity - have to create something both new and useful&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;zoom in and out of a problem to different levels of perspective&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&lt;li&gt;CHUNKING&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;How to form a chunk&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get a sense of the pattern you want to master for yourself&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Focus your undivided attention on the thing you want to chunk&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Understand the basic idea you&amp;rsquo;re trying to chunk (e.g. grasping the principle of supply and demand)&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;synthesize the gist, figure out the main idea&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;practice, explain for yourself&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;learn how to use the chunk&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Context - gain context to see not just how but also when to use the chunk&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;repeat and practice with related and unrelated problems to see when to use the chunk and when not to. this will help you see how it fits into the bigger picture&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Top down learning (big picture) and bottom up learning (chunking)&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;context is where top down learning and bottom up learning meet&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;learn the major or key concepts first&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;once you have this done, fill in the details&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;focused attention&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&lt;li&gt;understanding&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&lt;li&gt;practice&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Build a chunked library&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;To figure something out, 2 ways:&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;through sequential, step-by-step reasoning&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;each small step leads deliberately to a solution&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;requires focused mode&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;holistic intuition&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;requires diffused mode&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;serendipity&#34;&gt;serendipity&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Recall&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;After you read the material, look away and try to recall/practice what you&amp;rsquo;ve just read - you learn at a much deeper level than in other ways. the retrieval process itself helps deep learning.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Illusion of Competence&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Looking at a solution and thinking you understand it, this is not learning. you&amp;rsquo;ve done nothing to knit the concept into your neurocircuitry&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;You must have information persisting in your memory in order to truly master it, do creative things with it&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;With text/internet right in front of you, creates the illusion that you have learned it yourself. this is not true.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Test yourself (like recall) on what you&amp;rsquo;re learning - this will prove whether you&amp;rsquo;ve really grasped an idea&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Learn in various different environments&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Bigger Picture&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Dopamine - affects motivation. Released when we receive an unexpected reward.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Serotonin - affects your social life.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Emotions - highly affect learning, attention, and memory.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Library of Chunks&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Overlearning&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;continuing to study after you&amp;rsquo;ve mastered something.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;once you have a basic idea down,&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Deliberate practice - study the difficult stuff&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Einstellung (german for mindset) - need to unlearn erroneous older ideas&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;an idea you already have in your mind, or a neural pattern you&amp;rsquo;ve already developed, may prevent a better idea or solution from being found&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Interleaving - once you have a basic idea, start interleaving with different types of problems or techniques. mix up your learning. e.g. look ahead to a later chapter.&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;brain should get used to how to get used to an idea&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;how is not enough, need also to know when to use it&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Main Ideas&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Chunks - pieces of information that are bound together through use and often through meaning. They can be large and complex, but still take up only one slot in your working memory.&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Best built with 1) focused attention, 2) understanding, and 3) practice. Recall the best way way to learn chunks.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Transfer - chunks you&amp;rsquo;ve learned in one area can be useful for learning chunks in another area&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Test yourself to see whether you&amp;rsquo;re really learning the material&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Recall is an effective way to test yourself and to learn&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use deliberate practice (focus intently on the difficult parts of a problem) of what you find difficult to really learn/master&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;3.1 PROCRASTINATION&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Good learning is a bit by bit process. Space out your learning.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Chunking is related to habit, which frees our mind for other activities. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to think in a focused manner, it saves energy.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Habits/zombie mode&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cue - what might trigger you to go into zombie mode&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Routine - what you do in reaction to the cue. E.g. zombie mode, the routine response when it sees the cue.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reward - every habit continues because it rewards us - an immediate feeling of pleasure. find a way to reward good habits, like studying&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The belief - to change a habit, you need to change your underlying belief&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;If you find yourself avoiding tasks, focus on the process, not the product&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to spend 20 minutes writing&amp;rdquo; vs. &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to write three pages&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;To override a habit, change your reaction to a cue. this is the only place you have to use willpower.&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cue: location, time, how you feel, or reactions.&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Shut off your cues, e.g. your internet or phone&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The key to rewiring is to have a plan. Pick a favorite spot, eliminate distractions, and savor victories when the plan works.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Create a new reward after a routine.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The better you get at something, the more enjoyable it becomes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Belief - most important part - believe that you can do it. Believe that your new system works. To do this, create a new community of encouraging, like-minded people.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Write a weekly task list&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Then each day, write a daily to do list&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Write the to do task the day before.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Mix tasks up with your learning (can allow diffuse mode to set in!)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Plan your quitting time&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Work on the most important and disliked task first&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Law of serendipity - lady luck favors those who try&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Summary:&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Keep a planner journal&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Commit yourself to certain routines and tasks each day&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Savor the feelings of happiness of triumph&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Delay rewards until you finish the task&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Watch for procrastination cues&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Gain trust in your new system. Work hard when it&amp;rsquo;s time to work hard, relax and reward yourself when you&amp;rsquo;ve done your work.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Eat your frogs first - do the hardest thing first thing in the day&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;3.2 MEMORY&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Images/visualizing help encapsulate concepts&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The more senses you can engage, the deeper you can encode an idea&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Memory should be memorable/surprising, and it should be repeated. Writing and saying what you&amp;rsquo;re learning can enhance learning&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;handwriting helps to more deeply encode what you&amp;rsquo;re trying to learn&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Long Term Memory&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;You need to practice and repeat in order to store in LTM&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Practice should extend over several days&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Working memory&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Only four slots in working memory&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Memory palace&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Try to see, smell, feel, hear, things you are trying to remember&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Imagine a familiar place and attach ideas to parts of the room&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Create meaningful relationships between concepts and, e.g. associate numbers with noteworthy ages&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&lt;li&gt;BECOMING A BETTER LEARNER&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Exercise is one of the best things you can do for your brain&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;One of the best things you can do to understand a concept is to create a metaphor - the more visual, the better&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;metaphors useful for getting out of Einstellung&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Deliberate practice can help lift average brains to gifted&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;practice certain mental patterns, like practicing lifting weights&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Imposter syndrome - common and normal.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Change your thoughts, change your life&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Anyone can change their own brains&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Look up work of Cajal, neuroscientist&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;change your thoughts, change your life!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;What you learn through a single book/teacher is a partial version of a full 3-D reality of the subject, which has links to other subjects&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;look at other books, video, writings, etc.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;take responsibility for your own learning&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Empathy is good but also important to master dispassion, shut out people who may distract us from or not support our learning&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;take pride in who you are, defy present prejudices against others re what you can accomplish&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Hard start jump to easy technique&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Tough problems need lots of time, and often require the diffuse mode. So approach the hard problems first, but quickly jump to the easy ones.&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;This loads the hard problem into your mind, then when you shift to an easy problem, your unconscious mind can be working on the hard problem&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;You haven&amp;rsquo;t truly learned something until you teach it to others&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Writing&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Stop trying to be impressive and just start trying to be clear&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Once you are clear you&amp;rsquo;re going to be impressive&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Read closely the people you admire, study what you admire&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Think physically, don&amp;rsquo;t just write about abstract ideas, write about things. Ladder of abstract ideas.&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Look for physical correlates to your topic. Give the reader something to see&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;When you are out of ideas or feel like you have too little to say, step back and go into brainstorm mode. Mindmap. Brainstorm wildly. Draw ideas, make lists, etc. Shift the focus. Stop focusing on saying something important, and say something clear instead. Talk to a friend. Write questions down for yourself. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be an expert on what you&amp;rsquo;re writing about, you just have to be clear. Write down what puzzles you, write down what confuses you.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>On Deliberate Practice And Compounded Growth In Learning</title>
       <link>./posts/practice/</link>
       <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>./posts/practice/</guid>
       <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Skill is a result of focussed and consistent practice. When you are learning to improve, the initial rate of skill acquired is usually a flat line.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;A great quote from Ira Glass&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;“What nobody tells people who are beginners — and I really wish someone had told this to me … is that all of us who do creative work, we get into it because we have good taste. But there is this gap. For the first couple years you make stuff, and it’s just not that good. It’s trying to be good, it has potential, but it’s not. But your taste, the thing that got you into the game, is still killer. And your taste is why your work disappoints you. A lot of people never get past this phase. They quit. Most people I know who do interesting, creative work went through years of this. We know our work doesn’t have this special thing that we want it to have. We all go through this. And if you are just starting out or you are still in this phase, you gotta know it’s normal and the most important thing you can do is do a lot of work. Put yourself on a deadline so that every week you will finish one story. It is only by going through a volume of work that you will close that gap, and your work will be as good as your ambitions. And I took longer to figure out how to do this than anyone I’ve ever met. It’s gonna take awhile. It’s normal to take awhile. You’ve just gotta fight your way through.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you are learning something new, you usually start with a goal in mind. If you are like me, usually, you would start with a lofty goal in mind - an idea of how good you wish to become at the end of your endeavours. Honestly, there is nothing wrong with having a lofty goal to begin with. But as with most things in life, you rarely get something that you wish for without being patient enough or subsequent failures in your journey. Good things takes time and patience, and the process is heartbreaking for some. There are barriers to how better you can get in your estimated time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Initially, things would be really hard, and your results would be pretty lacklustre compared to the idea of success that you dream of. Lets say, you wake up one day and you decide you want to become a guitarist. You decide to go to the store to pick up a guitar and then you come home and start watching some youtube videos. In your head, you see yourself progressing to a level where you can play &lt;strong&gt;“All Along The Watchtower”&lt;/strong&gt; with a breeze in a matter of week. But then, as you gradually begin to pick up chords and learn to wrap your fingers around the fret board, it hits you, even the most basic chords takes time for you to get used to. It gets really frustrating at first,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TIME is your greatest enemy as well as your friend.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Be patient and don’t benchmark yourself with other achievers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As with every other thing in this world, you can keep reading and watching and talking about something, but unless you actually go out there and really do it, play it, you won’t improve.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Snowballing of Practice | CSS-Tricks &lt;a href=&#34;https://css-tricks.com/the-snowballing-of-practice/&#34;&gt;https://css-tricks.com/the-snowballing-of-practice/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How I Rewired My Brain to Become Fluent in Math - Issue 40: Learning - Nautilus &lt;a href=&#34;http://nautil.us/issue/40/learning/how-i-rewired-my-brain-to-become-fluent-in-math-rp&#34;&gt;http://nautil.us/issue/40/learning/how-i-rewired-my-brain-to-become-fluent-in-math-rp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably Overthinking It: Learning to program is getting harder &lt;a href=&#34;http://allendowney.blogspot.com/2018/02/learning-to-program-is-getting-harder.html&#34;&gt;http://allendowney.blogspot.com/2018/02/learning-to-program-is-getting-harder.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Beginner’s Guide to Deliberate Practice | James Clear &lt;a href=&#34;https://jamesclear.com/beginners-guide-deliberate-practice&#34;&gt;https://jamesclear.com/beginners-guide-deliberate-practice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Mired in a trough of disillusionment</title>
       <link>./posts/mired-in-a-trough-of-disillusionment/</link>
       <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>./posts/mired-in-a-trough-of-disillusionment/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 16, 2017·3 min read&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just 4 months left till I graduate from my college with a degree in Computer Science and I still can’t figure out what should I be doing after I graduate. It’s not that I don’t have options but it’s because there are just too many paths lying ahead and I don’t know which way is the best way to move forward.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And to worsen it all, my friends from school have already figured out what they want in their life and are well placed in Big 4 tech firms and consulting firms. It’s gotten so bad, that I hardly check my Facebook newsfeed to stop comparing myself with them. It’s not that I am jealous of them, it’s just I feel bad for not being focussed over the last 3 years in college. And Oh! two of my friends are already running their successful startups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./flowchart.png#full&#34; alt=&#34;Map my life&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I did 3 internships in the last 3 years and thankfully, I do have a full-time job offer from one of them. But, the companies that I really dream of seem so unreachable to me at this point of my life. Though, given 6 months of dedicated preparation, I can very well crack those interviews. Or perhaps not. But, the question is, should I really spend my time preparing for the interviews? I don’t know.Miles to go before I sleep!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With so many options lying ahead and all of them mutually exclusive, I know I will miss out on most of them if I pick just one and focus on only that path. And, that is something that has really affected my productivity to the extent that all I have been doing over the last 7 months is nothing but signing-up for multiple courses on Coursera, Udemy and Udacity, downloading tons of video lectures and ebooks and spending hours everyday just browsing the web and jumping from one blog to another. It has gotten so worse that sometimes I just feel overwhelmed with the sheer number of tabs opened on my browser at any point of time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;./focus.png&#34;&gt;focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Focus? What’s that?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So after being in the delirium for too long, I decided to change bases and move to a hackerspace called Jaaga on the outskirts of Bengaluru, India! It’s been almost a month now, I hope to write a post soon about my experiences at Jaaga!Md Halim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;near-term-goals&#34;&gt;Near Term Goals&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./goals.png&#34; alt=&#34;Goals&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
 </channel>
</rss>
